# Marvin Schmitt

MACHINE LEARNING SCIENTIST · PHD RESEARCHER

■ mail.marvinschmitt@gmail.com · 🎓 www.marvinschmitt.com · 🖸 marvinschmitt · 💆 @MarvinSchmittML

# SUMMARY

Machine learning scientist currently pursuing a PhD in computer science. Specializing in state-of-the-art machine learning algorithms, statistical modeling, and data visualization. 7+ years of hands-on experience in Python and R, with a comprehensive understanding of deep learning tools (TensorFlow and PyTorch). General problem solver with a passion for finding tailored and rigorous solutions to complex problems. Strong analytical skills combined with a talent for effectively communicating advanced concepts.

# EXPERIENCE

#### since 2021 PhD Researcher

### CLUSTER OF EXCELLENCE SIMTECH, UNIVERSITY OF STUTTGART, GERMANY

- Cyber Valley project: Meta-Uncertainty in Bayesian Model Comparison
- Researched state-of-the-art methods in deep learning, uncertainty quantification, and robustness
- Published scientific papers in top-tier machine learning venues: AISTATS, UAI
- Developed research software for deep learning, trustworthy machine learning, and data visualization.
- Managed student assistants and supervised student projects on probabilistic machine learning

#### 2017 – 2019 Business Consultant

#### **FREELANCE**

- · Instructed business workshops on communication, leadership, coaching, conflict, change, and personality
- · Programmed a manuscript generation software to create custom training material with Python, Flask, and LaTeX

#### 2017 – 2019 Network Officer

#### MARSILIUS-KOLLEG CENTER FOR ADVANCED STUDY, HEIDELBERG UNIVERSITY, GERMANY

- Implemented a robust live streaming concept based on UDP multicast (internal) and RTMP (external)
- Constructed a network-wide media center based on Samba
- · Maintained the website and digital knowledge base in Imperia CMS with HTML, CSS, PHP, and JavaScript

#### 2018 Research Intern

### QUANTITATIVE RESEARCH METHODS IN PSYCHOLOGY, HEIDELBERG UNIVERSITY, GERMANY

- Developed an algorithm to derive expectation measures from eye-tracking data
- Implemented machine learning methods to improve eye-tracking based usability research

### 2017 Consultant Intern

### MC HISCHE CONSULTING

- Advised the preparation and realization of business workshops
- Facilitated a book publication with focus on content, style guidelines, and typesetting

### 2016 – 2021 Tutor and Teaching Assistant

# Institute of Psychology, Heidelberg University, Germany

- · Taught seminars and tutorials about statistical inference, probabilistic modeling, and data science
- Conceptualized and graded student assignments, graded exams

# EDUCATION

### since 2021 PhD, Computer Science

#### CLUSTER OF EXCELLENCE SIMTECH, STUTTGART, GERMANY

- Advisors: Dr. Paul-Christian Bürkner, Prof. Dr. Andreas Bulling
- Expected graduation: 12/2024

### 2022 MSc, Data and Computer Science

### HEIDELBERG UNIVERSITY, GERMANY

- Grade 1.0 / 4.0 (A+; best: 1.0)
- · Master thesis: Visualization of Distribution and Uncertainty of Posterior Model Probabilities

### 2021 MSc, Psychology

### HEIDELBERG UNIVERSITY, GERMANY

- Grade 1.0 / 4.0 (A+; best: 1.0)
- Master thesis: Model Misspecification in Bayesian Parameter Estimation Tasks with Invertible Neural Networks

## 2018 BSc, Psychology

#### HEIDELBERG UNIVERSITY, GERMANY

- Grade 1.2 / 4.0 (A: best: 1.0)
- Bachelor thesis: Influence of Suggestive Questions on Usability Tests

# TEACHING

Summer 2022	<b>Lecture &amp; Exercise</b> , Statistical Inference at Fresenius UAS, Heidelberg
Summer 2022	<b>Exercise</b> , Bayesian Statistics and Probabilistic Machine Learning at University of Stuttgart
Winter 2021/22	<b>Lecture &amp; Exercise</b> , Statistical Inference at Fresenius UAS, Heidelberg
Winter 2021/22	<b>Seminar,</b> Introduction to Statistics with R for PhD researchers at Heidelberg University
Summer 2021	<b>Exercise</b> , Descriptive Statistics & Probability Theory at Fresenius UAS, Heidelberg
Summer 2021	<b>Lecture &amp; Exercise</b> , Statistical Inference at Fresenius UAS, Heidelberg

Winter 2020/21 **Seminar (TA),** Statistics with R at Heidelberg University

Winter 2020/21 **Lecture & Exercise,** Statistical Inference at Fresenius UAS, Heidelberg

Summer 2020 Seminar (TA), Programming with R at Heidelberg University
2020 Seminar, Communication Techniques at Fresenius UAS, Wiesbaden

2017 **Workshop,** Group Coaching at Fresenius UAS, Frankfurt

2016–2019 **Tutorial**, Descriptive Statistics, Probability Theory & Statistical Inference at Heidelberg University

# Extracurricular Activities & Awards

2019 – 2021	Scholarship holder, German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung d. dt. Volkes)
2018	Didactic certificate for tutors, Heidelberg University
2016 - 2021	Elected representative, Examination board M.Sc. & Diploma Psychology (break 10/2016 – 09/2017)
2016 - 2021	Elected representative, Institute Council (Fachrat) Psychology
2016 - 2020	Member, Student Council (Fachschaft) Psychology
2014	Award for remarkable social commitment, Auguste-Viktoria-Gymnasium Trier

# SELECTED INVOLVEMENT

**Consultant**Academic consultant in industry for Axem Neurotechnology (since 2022) **Reviewer**Reviewer for international scientific conferences (since 2022): ICML, AISTATS, AABI

# **EVENTS**

2023	Poster (contributed), AISTATS 2023, Valencia, Spain
2023	Talk (invited), Bayes Comp conference, Levi, Finland
2023	Poster (contributed), Bayes Comp conference, Levi, Finland
2022	Talk (invited), Cyber Valley: Writing workshop, consulting on students' AI short stories
2022	Poster (invited), ELLIS Unit Stuttgart Kickoff: Model misspecification in simulation-based inference
2022	Talk (invited), Cyber Valley: Office hours, Where does AI begin?
2022	<b>Talk (invited),</b> Blue Yonder Group Inc.: Validating synthetic training data in probabilistic machine learning
2022	<b>Participant,</b> 1st SimTech summer school: Knowledge-driven machine learning and its applications

# SKILLS

Languages	German (native), English (fluent), French (basic), Latin (basic), Norwegian (basic)
-----------	---

**Programming** Python, R, occasionally: C++, Java, JavaScript, HTML, CSS

**Data Science** Python (Tensorflow/keras, PyTorch, sklearn, scipy, numpy, pandas), R (brms, lme4, afex, tidyverse), Stan

Visualization Python (matplotlib, seaborn), R (ggplot2, plotly, rgl, shiny, gganimate), OpenGL

**Documentation** LaTeX (KOMA, tikZ), git, Imperia, Markdown, RMarkdown, Jupyter, sphinx, roxygen, Quarto

# **Publications**

- [1] F. Ewendt\*, M. Schmitt\*, A. Kluttig, J. Kühn, F. Hirche, F. B. Kraus, B. Ludwig-Kraus, R. Mikolajczyk, W. Wätjen, P.-C. Bürkner, M. Föller<sup>§</sup>, and G. I. Stangl<sup>§</sup>. Association between vitamin d status and eryptosis results from the german national cohort study. *Annals of Hematology*, 2023.
- [2] S. T. Radev, **M. Schmitt**, V. Pratz, U. Picchini, U. Köthe, and P.-C. Bürkner. JANA: Jointly amortized neural approximation of complex bayesian models. In *The 39th Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI)*, 2023.
- [3] **M. Schmitt**, S. T. Radev, and P.-C. Bürkner. Meta-uncertainty in bayesian model comparison. In *Proceedings of The 26th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics*, volume 206 of *PMLR*, pages 11–29, 2023.
- [4] **M. Schmitt**, P.-C. Bürkner, U. Köthe, and S. T. Radev. Detecting model misspecification in amortized Bayesian inference with neural networks. 2021. arXiv:2112.08866.